Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, And Station Employees Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, And Station Employees Records.
undated, 1910-1931.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Unknown.
1.5 linear feet.
MSS19890026
The Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, and Station Employees was organized in 1899, and was affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. Union name variants were the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees, AFL-CIO; the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks; and the Railway Clerks of America, Order. It was the largest single railroad organization for employees who devoted a majority of their time to clerical work of any description.
History
The Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, and Station Employees was organized in 1899, and was affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. Union name variants were the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees, AFL-CIO; the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks; and the Railway Clerks of America, Order. It was the largest single railroad organization for employees who devoted a majority of their time to clerical work of any description including chief clerks, foremen, train announcers, gatemen, checkers; parcel, baggage, and storeroom employees; dock and pier workers; train and engine crew callers; timekeepers; paymasters; freight inspectors; rate and tariff compilers; weigh masters; ticket clerks and sellers; operators of all office and station equipment devices; telephone and switchboard operators; and all employees occupying or performing duties similar to those mentioned. Males and females of good moral character with at least three months of experience in clerical work were eligible for membership. During the period of government control of the railroads, the union secured increases in wages and better working conditions.
The Grand Lodge was the legislative and judicial head of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks. It had jurisdiction in the United States, Central America, and Canada. No lodge, system, division, board of adjustment, or federation could be formed or continue to exist without the Grand Lodge's sanction. It had the sole right and power of granting and suspending charters, of receiving appeals, and of addressing grievances. The Grand Lodge executive officers included one grand president, seven vice grand presidents, and a grand secretary-treasurer. These officials also comprised the Grand Council. The grand president exercises general supervision over all lodges, system divisions, boards of adjustment, and federations of the Brotherhood, and over the Benefit Association. The grand vice presidents assisted the president in the discharge of his duties, performed others assigned to them, and provided a full written report at each regular convention. The grand secretary-treasurer was responsible for keeping a record of the proceedings of all conventions and furnishing a printed report of it to all lodges and system divisions in good standing, and to their members upon request. Other duties included making a report of all monetary and other transactions of his office to each convention, keeping records of all members, issues, notices of dues and assessments, and preparing and making available a semiannual report of the condition of the Brotherhood to all lodges and system divisions in good standing. Every lodge and subordinate organization had to report to the grand secretary-treasurer quarterly.
Union guidelines and regulations were described in the constitution, bylaws, statutes, and protective laws of the Grand Lodge. Subordinate lodges, divisions, and systems within the organization had similar documents stating their purpose and operations. To ensure uniformity in the union's administration, the Grand Lodge furnished charters, rituals, membership cards, and other forms throughout the United States and abroad. It also made the constitution d pertinent documents available in French, Spanish, and other languages in addition to English. By 1919, each lodge was to have one hundred members or less and systems divisions were supposed to hold meetings at least once a month. In contrast, the Grand Lodge convened once annually in a regular session on the first Monday in May. Fees and dues of the Lodges or system divisions were not to be less than three dollars for initiation. The amount of dues was determined by each lodge and subdivision and was not to be under six dollars per year.
In addition to the lodges, systems, and divisions, the union provided its members with other benefits. For example, all union members contributed to the Protective Fund. It helped to defray the expenses of conducting authorized strikes and of rendering financial assistance to those dismissed from service. There were also a General Fund and a Convention Fund. Another benefit was The Railway Clerk, the official publication of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks. It was intended to be published at least monthly to promote the general welfare of the union and the moral and intellectual character of its members. Notices, instructions, and information of interest to the membership were included. The annual subscription rate was fifty cents.
Scope and Content
The records date from 1910 to 1931, and include the union's business files, documentation of its internal functions, publications and correspondence to its members, and information on government regulation of railroads and railroad employees.
Many of records have been wrinkled, torn, or have portions missing. The entire collection was fumigated in 1991.
Arrangement
Series I: Governance ( 1910-1931 ) consists of five subseries, the first four are arranged chronologically, the last alphabetically:
Grand Lodge (1912-1931) includes the constitution, bylaws, statutes, and protective laws of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks. An application for membership, an obligation, and a ritual pamphlet are also in these files.
System Divisions (ca. 1919-1922) contains the bylaws of the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Systems Board of Adjustment and of the New York, New Haven, and Hartford and Central New England Systems Board of Adjustment.
Hartford Lodge Number 186 (1910-1922) includes bylaws, minutes, and a list of minutes, proceedings and correspondence for that lodge.
Conventions (1919-1925) consist of delegate identification forms, convention information, minutes, proceedings, and reports.
Forms (1919-1924) include such items as a strike ballot, benefit forms, a stock application, and salary statements.
Series II: Circulars and Weekly Letters ( 1919-1923 ) contains published circulars and correspondence for the Grand President of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks and from chairmen of the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Board of Adjustment. They are addressed to officers, representatives, chairmen, and members. These files cover the rates of pay, overtime, benefits, duties, positions, working conditions, an illegal strike, and the Clerks' National Agreement. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series III: Correspondence ( 1916-1931 ) contains general correspondence, notes, and notices from division and lodge presidents, chairmen, and agents. The files provide information on such topics as positions, duties, wages, hours, benefits, working conditions, seniority, and Brotherhood conventions. Also included are materials on the Hartford and New Haven Lodges, an illegal strike of the Nashville, Chattanooga, and Sedition Bill, and the Plumb Plan League. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Agreements and Resolutions ( 1913-1922 ) includes printed and typed agreements and resolutions between the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks and its lodges and stem boards of adjustment, as well as between the union and the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Company, and the General New England Railway Company. Subjects covered include government control of the railroads during World War I, position vacancies, seniority, promotions, hours of service, overtime, Sunday and holiday work, and working conditions. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series V: Decisions ( 1918-1923 ) consists of memoranda covering decisions on promotion and seniority, rates of pay for male and female employees, hours of service and working conditions, vacation, sick leave, discipline, and grievances. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series VI: New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad Company ( 1912-1924 ) includes a list of freight stations, an agreement with clerks outlining their duties and working conditions, ticket stubs, freight reports, pay rates and regulations, and a Hartford station clerk's roster. The material is arranged chronologically.
Series VII: United States Railroad Administration ( 1918-1919 ) includes publications from the Government Printing Office written by W.G. McAdoo, Director General of Railroads, and by his successor, Walker D. Hines. Among these materials are circulars, general orders, and interpretations and supplements to general orders. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series VIII: Alphabetical Files ( 1917-1922 ) consists of circulars and other publications, a Government Printing Office publications list, news clippings, a weight agreement, and similar related materials. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Series IX: Grievances ( 1916-1924 ) [RESTRICTED] consists mainly of typed and handwritten correspondence from union members to the grand president and other officials of Brotherhood lodges and divisions. Many of the documents are wrinkled or torn and a few have portions missing. Some decisions on grievances are included. The series is arranged chronologically, and, within individual files, the records are often grouped by topic.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to labor unions in Connecticut in addition to southern New England railroads, particularly the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight handlers, Express, and Station Employees.
Subjects:
Steamboat lines--Employees--Labor unions--United States.; Railroads--Employees--Labor unions--United States.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Resolutions.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection with the exception of materials in Series IX.
Custodial History
The records may have belonged to R.G. Stearns, chairman of the New York, New Haven, and Hartford Board of Adjustment, or to an official from Hartford Lodge Number 186.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by exchange from a dealer in 1989.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Governance, n. d., 1910 - 1931
  - Subseries A: Grand Lodge, undated, 1912-1931
    - Membership application and card, undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Obligation, undated (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Ritual, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Constitution, bylaws, and protective laws of the Grand Lodge, 1912, 1919 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Constitution, statutes, and protective laws of the Grand Lodge, 1922, 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - Constitution, statutes, and protective laws of the Grand Lodge, 1928, 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Subseries B: System Divisions, ca. 1919-1922
    - Bylaws of the NY, NH and H and CNE Systems Board of Adjustment, [1919?] (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Bylaws of the NY, NH and H System Board of Adjustment, 1919 October 8 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Representatives credentials to attend the 2/20/21 meeting of the NY, NH and H System Board of Adjustment, 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Recommendations of the bylaw committee of the NY, NH and H System Board of Adjustment, [1922?] (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Subseries C: Hartford Lodge Number 186, undated, 1910-1922
    - List of names and addresses, undated (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Bylaws, [1910s?] (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Letter to all members requesting attendance at 1/12/22 meeting, 1922 January 7 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Minutes 1/24/22, 1922 January 29 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Subseries D: Conventions, 1919-1925
    - Delegate identification forms—Cincinnati, OH, 1919 May (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Information to all officers and members of subordinate lodges and delegates-elect, 1919 April 8 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Minutes of Third Annual Convention of Ohio States Federation of the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks, 1920 October (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - Notes and report of Phil E. Ziegler to Third Triennial and 11th Regular Convention of the Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Dallas, TX, 1922 May (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Proceedings of 12th Regular and 4th Triennial Convention of the Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Kansas City, MO, 1925 May (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Subseries E: Forms, undated, 1919-1924
    - Benefits
      - Application for membership in Benefit Dept., undated (Box 1:, Folder 20)
      - Death benefit application, 1920s (Box 1:, Folder 21)
      - Death benefit membership certificate, 1925 November 25 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Official ballot—Strike and National Agreement Committee, 1919 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Salaries—rates of pay questionnaire, undated (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Loss of pay on account of reduction of force or abolishment of position form, 1920s (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Salaries
      - Statement of cost of living form A, 1922 March (Box 1:, Folder 26)
      - Rates of pay information, 1924 February 20 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
      - State of inequalities in rates of pay form D, 1924 February 22 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - Stock—application for shares in the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks National Bank of Cincinnati, 1923 March 8 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
- Series II: Circulars and Weekly Letters, 1919 - 1923
  - Timely Message. Articles reproduced from The Railway Clerk., 1909 December (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - General circular #3. Interpretation of Supplement #7, 1918 November 7 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Illegal strike on the N.C. and St. L. called by C.F. Jackson, 1919 April 7 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Nationwide agreement—increased pay and overtime, 1919 August 12 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - General circular #8. Voting, Nationwide agreement, National Agreement Committee, 1919 September 5 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - Weekly letters. Grand president to Vice grand presidents, general representatives, general chairmen, and all lodges, 1920-1921 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Minutes of the hearing by the U.S. Labor Board on the interpretation of rule 66 of the Clerks' National Agreement, 1921 December 8 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Monthly letter #8—rate of pay increases, 1923 May 19 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
- Series III: Correspondence, undated, 1916 - 1931
  - undated (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - 1918 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 40)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1919 August 25 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - 1919 January - June (Box 1:, Folder 42)
  - 1919 August - December (Box 1:, Folder 43)
  - 1920 January - June (Box 1:, Folder 44)
  - 1920 August - December (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - 1921 January - February (Box 1:, Folder 46)
  - 1921 March - May (Box 1:, Folder 47)
  - 1921 June - December (Box 1:, Folder 48)
  - 1922 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 49)
  - 1923 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 50)
  - 1923 April - December (Box 1:, Folder 51)
  - 1924 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 52)
  - 1925 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 53)
  - 1927, 1929, 1931 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
- Series IV: Agreements and Resolutions, 1913 - 1922
  - Settlement of the differences and the agreement reached between the NY, NH and H RR and the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks, 1913 June 3 (Box 1:, Folder 55)
  - Fresno Lodge #90, Fresno, CA. Resolutions concerning government controls, 1919 February 27 (Box 1:, Folder 56)
  - Rules in the proposed agreement between the NY, NH and H RR, General NE Railway Co., and the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks, 1921 July 13 (Box 1:, Folder 57)
  - Tentative draft of the agreement following the issuance of decision #119 and the disputed rules handed down by the Labor Board on decision #630 (docket 475), 1922 February 10 (Box 1:, Folder 58)
  - Agreement in consideration of receiving advertisements and subscriptions to the year book and shippers' guide from Lodge #486, Brotherhood of Railway Clerks, 1922 April (Box 1:, Folder 59)
- Series V: Decisions, 1918 - 1923
  - Supplement #7 to general order #27—promotion and seniority, 1918 September 1 (Box 1:, Folder 60)
  - Docket C-400. Railway Board of Adjustment #3—NY, NH and H RR v. Clerks, 1919 November 13 (Box 1:, Folder 61)
  - Decision #113 (Docket 210)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. Chicago and Alton RR, 1921 April 7 (Box 1:, Folder 62)
  - Decision #460 (Docket 636)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. Gulf and Ship Island RR, 1921 December 1 (Box 1:, Folder 63)
  - Decision #463 (Docket 678)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. Gulf and Ship Island RR, 1921 December 1 (Box 1:, Folder 64)
  - Decision #475 (Docket 911)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. Chicago, Milwaukee, and St. Paul Railway, 1921 December 1 (Box 1:, Folder 65)
  - Decision #578 (Docket 939)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. NY, NH and H RR, 1921 December 1 (Box 1:, Folder 66)
  - Decision #630 (Docket 475)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. NY, NH, and H RR, CNE Railway, 1922 April 19 (Box 1:, Folder 67)
  - Decision #1668 (Docket 2166)—Brotherhood of Railway Clerks v. NY, NH, and H RR, CNE Railway, 1923 March 5 (Box 1:, Folder 68)
- Series VI: New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Company, 1912 - 1924
  - List of freight stations, 1912 January 3 (Box 1:, Folder 69)
  - Agreement with clerks, 1913 January 11 (Box 1:, Folder 70)
  - Signs, ticket stubs, register receipts, exchange trip pass, business card, 1914-1920 (Box 1:, Folder 71)
  - Transportation application; freight reports; shipping order; uniform tracer for delayed freight, 1916-1917 (Box 1:, Folder 72)
  - Receipts, cashier's checks, delivery check, waybill statements, freight bill, 1917-1921 (Box 1:, Folder 73)
  - Reports from OS and D [Order, shipment and Delivery?], 1919 May - August (Box 1:, Folder 74)
  - Schedules—conductors, trainmen, yardmen, 1920 May 1 (Box 1:, Folder 75)
  - Circular letter to clerks—rules awarded by U.S. Labor Board in decision #630, 1922 April 10 (Box 1:, Folder 76)
  - Clerks roster—Hartford, CT station, 1923 May 7, 1924 January 15 (Box 1:, Folder 77)
- Series VII: United States Railroad Administration, 1918-1919
  - General order #27—wages of railroad employees, 1919 May 25 (Box 1:, Folder 78)
  - Public service and accounting circular #16, 1918 July 11 (Box 1:, Folder 79)
  - Supplement #6 to general order #27—interpretation of wage orders, 1918 August 30 (Box 1:, Folder 80)
  - Supplement #7 to general order #27—rates of pay and rules for overtime, 1918 September 1 (Box 1:, Folder 81)
  - Interpretation #1 to supplement #7 to general order #27—overtime, 1918 November 23 (Box 1:, Folder 82)
  - Transportation of spirituous and intoxicating liquors into no license towns of MA, 1918 December 16 (Box 1:, Folder 83)
  - Interpretation #15 to supplement #7 to general order #27—Checkers, 1919 May 7 (Box 1:, Folder 84)
  - Interpretation #16 to supplement #7 to general order #27, 1919 May 6 (Box 1:, Folder 85)
  - Interpretation #17 to general order #27, 1919 May 7 (Box 1:, Folder 86)
  - Interpretation #20 to supplement #7 to general order #27, 1919 October 23 (Box 1:, Folder 87)
- Series VIII: Alphabetical Files, undated, 1917-1922
  - American Federation of Labor, Railway Employees Department—special circular, 1920 May 27 (Box 1:, Folder 88)
  - Help Our Soldiers and Sailors: Establish Committees for the Benefit of Our Returning Soldiers and Sailors—Advisory Commission of the Council of National Defense, 1919 April 18 (Box 1:, Folder 89)
  - Maine Central Railroad—weight agreement, 1917 February 16 (Box 1:, Folder 90)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, meeting minutes, employee promotion and seniority, undated (Box 1:, Folder 91)
  - News clippings—Sherman Anti-Trust Act, railroad clerk wage cuts, college graduates in the railroad business, [1922?] (Box 1:, Folder 92)
  - Plumb Plan League—convention address, membership application, pamphlet, 1920 (Box 1:, Folder 93)
  - Transportation—Railroad and shipping problems, Postal service, Telegraphs, Telephones, Government ownership and control—list of Publications by the GPO, 1921 April (Box 1:, Folder 94)
- Series IX: Grievances, undated, 1916-1924
  - undated (Box 2:, Folder 95)
  - 1916, 1918 (Box 2:, Folder 96)
  - 1919 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 97)
  - 1919 May - December (Box 2:, Folder 98)
  - 1920 (Box 2:, Folder 99)
  - 1921 (Box 2:, Folder 100)
  - 1922 (Box 2:, Folder 101)
  - 1923 (Box 2:, Folder 102)
  - 1924 (Box 2:, Folder 103)